in this video we're going to look at our
second example of spinners in physics
which involves the stair and gearlock
experiment and how it reveals the
existence of quantum spin States
we're going to find that the mathematics
used to describe Quantum spin States is
the exact same as the mathematics used
to describe the polarizations of
classical light waves that we saw in the
last two videos
they are both described by two by one
complex columns called Spinners that can
be rotated with su2 matrices and there
is an angle doubling relationship
between physical space and the quantum
State space
just like how we saw there was an angle
doubling relationship between
polarization space and physical space in
the last video
before getting to the spinner
mathematics let's describe the stair and
gerlock experiment which was performed
in 1922. I'm going to call it the SG
experiment for short
the SG experiment involves a beam of
neutral atoms and an inhomogenous
magnetic field
a homogeneous magnetic field would have
the same strength everywhere but this
strangely shaped magnetic device is able
to generate an inhomogenous magnetic
field which is stronger at this pointed
tip labeled South and weaker on the
lower half labeled North
the beam of neutral atoms in the
original experiment was made of silver
atoms neutral atoms have an equal number
of protons and electrons so there is no
net charge
naively you'd expect neutral atoms to be
completely unaffected by a magnetic
field but the Bohr model of the atom
that was developed in the early 1900s
predicted that electrons orbited around
the nucleus and this small Loop of
electric current would behave like a
magnetic dipole or a tiny bar magnet
now if we were to send a bunch of tiny
classical bar magnets through this
inhomogenous magnetic field then the bar
magnets with North pointing up would be
deflected upward since the magnetic
field is stronger at this tip
and magnets with North pointing down
would be deflected downward
and every other orientation of bar
magnet would be deflected somewhere in
between depending on their orientation
however after performing The Experiment
this is not what we see we only see two
types of deflection either completely up
or completely down and nothing in
between
this experiment shows us that when we
measure the angular momentum of a silver
atom there are only two possible
discrete results and so the angular
momentum of silver atoms is quantized
in later years this magnet-like behavior
of silver atoms was found to be not due
to the electrons orbital angular
momentum around the nucleus
it was later discovered that the Bohr
model was wrong and that electron
orbitals come in various shapes
the first 46 electrons in a silver atom
have no net orbital angular momentum
overall the final 47th electron exists
in the spherical 5S orbital which also
has no net orbital angular momentum
so electron orbitals do not generate a
magnetic field here
instead the magnetic dipole in silver
atoms is due to the 47th electrons
internal angular momentum also called
spin angular momentum
this internal angular momentum is
sometimes envisioned as being due to the
electron spinning on an axis like a ball
however in reality electrons are
described by wave functions and are not
tiny spinning balls so this explanation
also fails to explain the magnetic
dipole
the concept of an electron having
internal angular momentum has a
reputation for being very difficult to
understand
however there's an analogy with light
that can help our understanding here
matter particles have orbital angular
momentum when they actually curve around
in space and light rays can also have
orbital angular momentum when they curve
around in space
but from our last video we know that
light waves can be polarized which
allows for an internal type of angular
momentum that is internal to the light
beam itself
modern Quantum field Theory tells us
that matter particles can also have
something similar to a polarization
which gives them internal angular
momentum that's internal to the
particles field instead of being due to
curved paths in physical space
but we're not going to focus on Quantum
fields for now for this video we just
want a basic experimental understanding
of the quantized spin angular momentum
of electrons we'll get this
understanding by sending a beam of atoms
through multiple SG experiments
to start let's review some of the
notation and Mathematics used in quantum
mechanics
In classical mechanics when we talk
about the state of a particle we're
referring to the particle's position and
momentum and how these quantities change
over time
but in quantum mechanics a particle's
state is instead represented by an
abstract State Vector which Loosely
speaking is the same thing as the
particle's wave function
everything that we can possibly know
about a particle like its position
momentum and energy can be derived from
the particle's state vector
this idea of an abstract State Vector
can be a bit confusing but hopefully it
will become more clear as the video goes
on
the standard way of writing a vector in
physics is to write a little arrow above
the variable but in quantum mechanics we
use the KET Vector notation and write
vectors like this with an angle bracket
pointing to the right
we can write cat factors as linear
combinations of basis vectors as we
normally do or write the components of
the vector in a column like this
four vectors with real components we can
get the squared length of a vector v by
writing V transpose V
but in quantum mechanics Vector
components can be complex numbers so we
get the squared length of a vector by
doing the transpose conjugate times V
this extra complex conjugate ensures our
final result for the magnitude is real
the transpose complex conjugate is
called the hermitian conjugate of a
vector and this is written with a dagger
symbol
in quantum mechanics we write the
hermitian conjugate of cat vectors like
this with an angle bracket that's
pointing left these are called bra
vectors
you can Loosely think of cat vectors as
columns and Loosely think of bra vectors
as rows
when multiplied together they give a
single number this is called their inner
product
now one of the strange Concepts in
quantum mechanics is the idea of wave
function collapse
this is the idea that a particle can be
in a superposition of several States but
as soon as we measure the particle it
will collapse into a single state
According to some probabilistic rules
mathematically Quantum superpositions
are represented by linear combinations
where each basis Vector represents one
of the possible States the system can
collapse to
the coefficients in the linear
combination are called probability
amplitudes and they are related to the
probability of measuring each state
after the collapse
in the SG experiment there are only two
states the particle can collapse to
either spin up denoted with an up Arrow
cut or spin down denoted with a down
arrow cut
the rules for determining the
probabilities for collapsing into a
given state are given by Bourne's rule
in simplified form Bourne's rule tells
us that when we want to know the
probability of some State a collapsing
onto a state B after a measurement this
probability equals the squared magnitude
of the inner products of the states A
and B written in brockette notation like
this
this inner product is sort of like the
overlap between the two State vectors A
and B if we were to cast A's Shadow onto
B
the process of casting B's Shadow onto a
gives us the same result except complex
conjugated
however since the probabilities we
measure are the squared lengths of these
inner product overlaps it doesn't matter
which direction we measure the overlaps
in
so the squared magnitude of these two
inner products are equal
now let's use born's rule to try and
understand the quantum states in the SG
experiment better
we'll do this by putting particles
through multiple SG experiments in a row
to simplify the diagrams a bits I'm
going to replace these magnets by a box
with the letter Z on it this indicates
the nhomogeneous magnetic field points
in the Z Direction
I'm also going to rewrite the spin up
and spin down States AS Plus said and
minus said indicating the coordinate
directions that the particles are
deflected in
let's say that the particles in the
initial beam are in some State PSI after
going through the SG apparatus they
collapse into one of two states either
spin up or spin down
let's take the spin up particles and put
them through another SG apparatus
we find that all the particles are
deflected up and none are deflected down
so according to Bourne's rule the
probability of measuring spin up given a
spin up state is one and the probability
of measuring spin down given a spin up
state is zero
now let's put an SG apparatus after the
down States as you might expect all the
particles are deflected down
so Bourne's rule tells us the
probability of measuring spin down from
spin down is one and the probability of
measuring spin up from spin down is zero
all of these inner product relationships
from born's rule give us some useful
information about the spin up and spin
down state vectors
for example it tells us that the spin
Upstate has a magnitude of one and the
spin down state also has a magnitude of
one
also the spin up and spin down states
are orthogonal since their inner product
is zero
so in physical space up and down are
separated by a turn of 180 degrees
but in our Quantum State space where the
particle spin States live the spin up
and spin down states are orthogonal so
they are 90 degrees apart
so we're already starting to see that
there's an angle doubling relationship
between physical space and the quantum
State space
next we'll try the exact same setup
except rotating the SG apparatuses by 90
degrees so that the magnetic fields are
oriented in the direction of the x-axis
so that particle beams are split into
the plus X and minus X directions
performing the exact same experiments as
above we get born rule formulas for the
plus X state
and the minus X state
these inner product formulas tell us
that the plus X and minus X states have
magnitudes of one and the plus X and
minus X states are orthogonal
now let's try something more interesting
let's arrange the first SG apparatus so
that it points in the X Direction and
then send the plus X particle beam
through a second SG apparatus pointing
in the Z Direction
we find that the plus X particle beam is
split evenly in the plus set and minus Z
directions
taking borne's rule again the
probability of measuring plus said from
plus X is one-half
and the probability of measuring minus
said from plus X is also one half
if we repeat the experiment but starting
with the minus X beam instead we also
find a 50 50 split between the plus set
and minus Z States
so the plus X and minus X states can
each collapse into the plus set or minus
Z States when a magnetic field in the Z
direction is applied
this is telling us that the plus X State
can be written as a Quantum
superposition of the plus Z and minus Z
states with the proper coefficients
because it can collapse into either one
after a measurement
and remember Quantum superposition is
just a fancy way of saying linear
combination
in order to get the expected
probabilities of one-half from the
experiment we need to set the
coefficients for plus X to be one over
the square root of two and one over the
square root of two
you can check that applying a plus said
bra Vector to a plus Z cat vector and
then squaring the results gives us the
expected probability of one-half
the same goes for applying the negative
Z state to the plus X state
the minus X state uses the coefficients
plus one over the square root of two and
minus one over the square root of two
this also reproduces the expected
probabilities of one-half
and importantly this choice of
coefficients makes the plus X and minus
X states orthogonal with an inner
product of zero and also makes each have
a magnitude of one as expected
looking at our Quantum spin space the
plus X and minus X States look like this
this continues with the expected angle
doubling relationship with physical
space where a 45 degree turn in Quantum
spin space is a 90 degree turn in
physical space
next let's look at a pair of SG
experiments pointing along the y-axis
looking at the born rules we see that
the plus Y and minus y states have
magnitudes of 1 and are orthogonal
if we start with a y aligned SG
apparatus and then feed the plus y
particle beam into a z-aligned SG
apparatus we once again find a 50 50
split between the plus Z and minus Z
States
the same occurs if we begin with the
minus y particle beam
so the plus Y and minus y States can be
written as Quantum superpositions of
plus said and minus said because they
can collapse into either one
but if we want to write the Y States as
Quantum superpositions of the plus Z and
minus Z States we run into a problem
we've already used the coefficients of
plus one over the square root of 2 and
-1 over the square root of two for our
spin plus X and minus X States and we
can't reuse those coefficients
so what coefficients can we pick that
will still give us probabilities of 50
percent
the secret is to start using complex
numbers
we'll write the plus y State as a
superposition of plus Z and minus Z
using the coefficients one over the
square root of 2 and I over the square
root of two
if we calculate the inner product of the
plus Z and plus y States and then find
the squared magnitude we get the
expected probability of one-half
the same thing happens for the inner
product of the minus Z and plus y States
the imaginary I goes away when we take
the squared amplitude
for the minus y State we use
coefficients of one over the square root
of two and minus I over the square root
of 2.
this gives the expected probabilities of
one-half
this also ensures that the plus Y and
minus y states are orthogonal with an
inner product of zero
and also ensures their magnitudes are
one
as an exercise you can check that the
inner product of one of the X states
with one of the Y States always gives a
squared magnitude of one-half and you
can also think about what this means in
terms of the results of the
corresponding SG experiments
so if we look at all the quantum
superposition formulas we've written so
far these relationships exactly match
the formulas for the Jones vectors we
saw in the previous two videos
we can flip back and forth between them
using this dictionary
it also turns out that we can arrange
these six Quantum States on a sphere
like this aligning them with the
directions and physical space that they
actually represent
this sphere is called the block sphere
this is mathematically equivalent to the
point array sphere we saw in the last
video where these six main polarizations
of light are also arranged on a sphere
with LightWave polarizations we could
mix the polarizations together in
various ways to get any polarization on
this sphere including elliptical
polarizations
similarly we can mix the quantum States
in various superpositions to give any
state on this sphere these correspond to
States associated with SG experiments
that are aligned at arbitrary directions
in space
we showed in the last video that we
could rotate vectors across these
spheres using two by two unitary
matrices written as U2 for short
remember rotating a vector PSI with a
matrix u means that it's squared
magnitude won't change
so the squared magnitude formula should
be equal before and after the rotation
we can show that these matrices must
have the property that U inverse equals
U dagger which is the definition of a
unitary Matrix
now it turns out that for rotating these
Quantum states on the sphere U2 matrices
are too General because we've missed an
important fact about born's rule
as we already know Bourne's rule tells
us that the probability of measuring a
state a collapsing into a state B is the
squared magnitude of the inner product
of A and B
now let's modify the state a by giving
it a complex phase Factor e to the I
Theta if we now calculate the
probability of our new a state
collapsing into State B we get the
squared magnitude of this inner product
the phase e to the I Theta gets a
negative sign due to the required
hermitian conjugate
since e to the I Theta is just a scalar
number we can pull it outside of the
inner product
and here the magnitude of a product is
the same thing as the product of the
magnitudes and the magnitude of a
complex phase e to the I Theta is just
one because it lives on the complex unit
circle
so the probability formula we get is
unchanged compared to before
so we know that when we measure the
state a it can collapse into various
other states According to some known
probabilities
and we just learned that when we measure
the state a multiplied by a phase Factor
it can collapse into the exact same set
of states with the exact same
probabilities
because the states A and A times phase
collapse into the exact same states with
the exact same probabilities practically
speaking there is no difference between
them
in real quantum mechanics experiments
all we can do is perform experiments
over and over again and keep score of
the results we get
if one scientist did experiments with
State a and another scientist did
experiments with State a times phase
they would find all the statistics of
their experimental results are the exact
same
so physically speaking State a and state
a times phase are actually the same
physical state even if the vectors look
different the two vectors give the exact
same physics
so in quantum mechanics a physical state
is unchanged when we multiply its vector
by an overall phase such as I negative 1
or any other complex phase
now recall we said that U2 matrices will
perform rotations on our block sphere of
States but since overall phases don't
matter there are multiple U2 matrices
that can rotate us to the same output
State each Matrix with a different
overall phase so there is some
redundancy in the group of U2 matrices
in order to pick a unique U2 Matrix for
doing rotations on our block sphere we
pick the specific U2 Matrix whose
determinant is one
remember we can always set the
determinant of a U2 Matrix to plus one
by multiplying it by the correct complex
phase
this restricts us to su2 the group of
two by two unitary matrices with
determinants of plus one
so in conclusion the behavior of quantum
spin States is mathematically equivalent
to the behavior of Jones vectors and
light polarizations both are represented
by two component complex columns which
can be represented geometrically on a
sphere
we can rotate between points on the
sphere using su2 matrices since both
Quantum States and light polarizations
don't care about overall phase factors
which includes not caring about overall
negative signs
in the case of physical space for wave
polarizations and the quantum State
space for Quantum spin States these are
spaces where the overall negative signs
are still visible
however when we move to the point array
sphere and block sphere where the
overall phases don't matter there is no
difference between a vector's positive
version and its negative version
so one rotation in the original space
corresponds to two rotations on these
mathematical spheres where overall
negative signs are ignored
this is the source of the angle doubling
relationships between the two spaces and
why these two by one complex columns are
called spinners
now we've described the basic
mathematics of spinners as two by one
columns that rotate with su2 matrices
and don't care about overall phase
factors
but it's possible you still find this
pretty confusing so in our next video
we're going to show how we can visualize
Spinners as flag pulls on a sphere and
show how these Spinners are really
elements of a space called the complex
projective line
this will hopefully make all the
mysterious mathematical properties of
spinners disappear and make them seem
more like common sense